A Guide to the Williams Family Papers, 1819-1993
Thomas Balch Library
Additional materials in the estate papers document the management of property in Buffalo. There is correspondence with the Marine Trust Co. of Buffalo about multiple mortgages and transfers of securities in the early 1930s. Other estate papers include accounts and inventories.
Subseries XII: Harrison and Joan Stafford-Allen Williams, 1937
There is one item for Harrison and Joan Stafford-Allen Williams, the passenger list from the S.S. Penland, the ship on which they met in 1937. Joan Stafford-Allen Williams' correspondence contains three letters from 1946 about Harrison Williams' death.
Subseries XIII: Harrison Williams Jr., 1904-1928
Harrison Williams Jr.'s collection is comprised of a small number of cards, a letter from his uncle, Gordon, enclosing postcards from Germany during World War II, his obituary, and undated bookplates.
Subseries XIV: Winslow Williams, 1913-1993
Winslow Williams' papers contain a small amount of correspondence from his family, particularly as a boy and young man. There are a number of letters in 1933 concerning the death of his mother, Pauline. There is a gap until the later part of his life when he began to correspond with newly discovered relatives, the Texas descendents of Jonas Harrison, in the 1980s. Other materials include financial papers such as a farm account book, which also has information about his photography business, two items regarding property from the Nathan Winslow estate, and a debarkation card from a trip at sea with his father aboard the S.S. President Garfield from 1935-1936.
Subseries XV: Winslow and Constance Williams, 1936-1937
Winslow and Constance Williams' shared collection includes telegrams on the occasion of their marriage in 1937, and memorabilia from their honeymoon trip to South America such as postcards and a ship's menu.
Subseries XVI: Helen Constance Moore Williams, 1937-1991
Helen Constance Moore Williams' papers contain a small number of items including clippings about her engagement and marriage to Winslow, a birthday card made by her daughter Constance, and the memorial from her funeral in 1991.
Series V: Winslow Family, 1880-1937
Subseries I: Nathan Winslow, 1880
There is one item each for Nathan Winslow, a copy of his will showing divisions of his interest in properties in Ohio and Illinois.
Subseries II: Mary A. Winslow, 1885
There is one item for Mary Winslow, a copy of her will which further divided percentage interests by the heirs in the Ohio and Illinois properties.
Subseries III: Richard Winslow Estate, 1901-1937
Richard Winslow estate papers contain copies of legal documents. Winslow left two wills, one in Cuyahoga County, OH and one in France regarding property he owned in that country. Winslow's estate was complicated by his residual interest in the Euclid Ave. property and because all trustees and executors had died by 1915. Harrison Williams appears to have acquired copies of records in his capacity as legal counsel for Pauline.
Subseries IV: William G. Winslow, 1903-1934
William G. Winslow estate papers contain copies of legal documents such inventories, accountings, decrees, and agreements. There are some duplicate copies and transcribed copies, the latter of which includes three letters. The documents appear to have been acquired by Harrison Williams.
Subseries V: William Gaston Winslow, 1903-1911
William Gaston Winslow's papers consist of three letters, including two from M. Marechal (n.d.) in Lancey, Switzerland written in French. There is a note on one of the envelopes reading "keep these always for my sake, Pauline, Father."
Subseries VI: Annie Chadwick Estate, 1924-1927
Annie Chadwick's estate papers contain a small number of legal documents. Her estate was complicated by the fact that she left real property in Paris and in Montreuil-sur-Mer in France in addition to her interests in the Euclid Ave. property.
Series VI: Miscellaneous, photographs, oversized documents, and artifacts
There are a small number of miscellaneous items. Of interest are a collection of 30 Civil War envelopes featuring pro-Union propaganda images and slogans, an embroidery pattern book, an almanac from 1848, and postcards from Woodrow Wilson's inauguration in 1917.
Visual materials in the collection include photographs, photograph albums, cartes de visite, and negatives. Most of the photographs are identified, and include portraits of family members and scenic views. A few of the images are photographs of portraits in oil, including James C. Harrison and Griffin Stedman Williams. The negatives were taken by Winslow Williams of people and scenes; many are undated but probably originate from the late 1940s to 1950s. Numbers associated with many of the negatives reflect his practice with photographs in his business. Seven albums of photographs belonging to Winslow Williams contain pictures from vacations and other events, and have been re-housed for preservation purposes. There are also photograph albums, tintypes, cased daguerreotypes, and color stereo slides housed with the artifact collection.
Oversized documents include a series of letters from Samuel Asbury to Harrison Williams. Removal sheets have been placed in the collection with the location and date of each oversized letter. Other items include receipts, Griffin Stedman Williams' appointment as commercial agent for the United States at Nottingham England and his Special Passport, and Gordon Williams' passport for his trip on behalf of the American Fund for French Wounded.
Photographic material in the artifact collection includes a photograph album of Harrison and Pauline Williams' wedding trip to Europe 1911, two albums belonging to Winslow Williams, and an 1862-1869 album belonging to Griffin Stedman Williams. There is also a scrapbook kept by Winslow Williams with photographs and memorabilia, which is in fragile condition. Other photographs include a small number of daguerreotypes and tintypes, most of which are not identified or dated.
The collection contains a variety of artifacts such as a stamp moistener, calling card plates, a Valentine's Day memento from Harrison Williams to Pauline, wedding books, and a notebook containing poetry written by Harrison Williams as a boy. Other items include a pair of slippers worn by Mary Harrison Williams at her wedding, a series of cards strung together on a string with Asian writing, and a piece of wedding cake from Harrison and Pauline Williams' wedding. Also of interest is a collection of railroad passes from 20 different railroads from the late 19th century and early 20th century.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Albany Argus, 03/15/1814, http://www.genealogybank.com/gbnk/.com
Ancestry Library Edition, United States census, military enlistment records, Social Security death register, http://www.ancestrylibrary.com
Asbury, Samuel E., "Jonas Harrison, Legendary and Historical," Volume 45, Number 3, Southwestern Historical Quarterly Online, http://www.tshaonline.org/publications/journals/shq/online/v045/n3/contrib_DIVL4249.html [Accessed Mon Sep 8 9:02:11 CDT 2008]
Biographical Directory of the United States Congress, http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=W000544
Clark, Robert L.; Lee, Craig A.; Wilson, Jack W. "Managing a Pension Portfolio in the Nineteenth Century: The U.S. Navy Pension Fund, 1800-1840," Business and Economic History, Volume 28, no. 2, Fall 1999. http://www.h-net.org/~business/bhcweb/publications/BEHprint/v028n1/p0093-p0104.pdf
Cullum, George W. Biographical Register of the Officers and Graduates of the U.S. Military Academy at West Point New York Since Its Establishment in 1802, Supplement Volume VI-A, 1910-1920. Saginaw, Mich.: Seemen and Peters, Printers, 1920. http://books.google.com
Cutter, William Richard. Genealogical and Family History of Western New York. New York: Lewis Historical Publishing Company, 1912. http://books.google.com
Davis, Charles Henry Stanley. History of Wallingford, Conn. from its Settlement in 1670 to the Present Time. Meriden, CT: Charles Henry Stanley Davis, 1870. http://books.google.com
Dudley, William S. ed. The Naval War of 1812: A Documentary History, Vol. II 1813. Secretary of the Navy's Advisory Committee on Naval History, Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Printing Office, 1992.
Dudley, William S. ed. The Naval War of 1812: A Documentary History, Vol. III 1814-1815. Secretary of the Navy's Advisory Committee on Naval History, Superintendent of Documents, U.S. Government Printing Office, 1992.
Encyclopedia of Cleveland History. Entry: Dauby, Nathan L. http://ech.cwru.edu/ech-cgi/article.pl?id=DNL
Encyclopaedia Britannica, http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/392187/Anne-Tracy-Morgan
Essex Register, 01/01/1814, http://www.genealogybank.com/gbnk/
Hall, Clayton Coleman, ed. Baltimore: Its History and Its People, Volume II - Biography. New York & Chicago: Lewis Historical Publishing Company, 1912. http://books.google.com
Handbook of Texas Online, s.v."Shannon, Owen," http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/SS/fsh47.html
Handbook of Texas Online, s.v. "Texas Revolution," http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/TT/qdt1.html
Hansen, Arlen J. Gentleman Volunteers. New York: Arcade Publishing, Inc., 1996. http://books.google.com
The History of Buffalo: A Chronology, 1841-1865, http://www.buffaloah.com/h/1865.html#1854
Holton, David-Parsons and Frances K. Forward Holton. Winslow Memorial: Family Records of Winslows and Their Descendents in America with the English Ancestry as Far as Known. Kenelm Winslow, v. II. New York: Mrs. Frances K. Holton, 1888. http://books.google.com
Inter Ocean, October 8, 1892, http://www.genealogybank.com/gbnk/
Joblin, Maurice. Cleveland Past and Present. 1869. http://www.fullbooks.com/Cleveland-Past-and-Present1.html
Loudoun Times, July 26, 1928.
Loudoun Times Mirror, November 19, 1936; June 13, 1946; April 8, 1965; June 16, 1977; February 24, 1993; March 10, 1993
Library of Congress Authorities, http://authorities.loc.gov/
Natural History Museum, Los Angeles County. Guide to the Photograph Collections, http://www.nhm.org/site/research-collections/seaver-center/photograph-collections-guide
New England Historical and Genealogical Register, volume 14. Boston: Samuel G. Drake, 1860. http://books.google.com
New York State Military Museum and Veterans Research Center, NYS Division of Military and Naval Affairs, 65th Regiment Infantry New York Volunteers Spanish-American War, http://www.dmna.state.ny.us/historic/reghist/spanAm/infantry/65thInfMain.htm
Ohio History Central: An On-Line Encyclopedia of Ohio History, http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/entry.php?rec=1004
Peterson, Dorothy Burns. Daughters of Republic of Texas. http://books.google.com
The Pioneer Families of Cleveland, http://www.heritagepursuit.com/Cuyahoga/Cleveland602.htm
The Political Graveyard, http://politicalgraveyard.com/
Ratigan, William. Great Lakes Shipwrecks & Survival. Michigan: William B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1977. http://books.google.com
Robison, W. Scott. History of the City of Cleveland: Its Settlement, Rise and Progress. Cleveland, Ohio: Robison & Cockett, 1887. http://books.google.com
Rose, William Ganson. Cleveland: The Making of a City. Cleveland, Ohio: The World Publishing Company, 1950.
Smith, Henry Perry. History of the City of Buffalo and Erie County, with Illustrations and Biographical Sketches of Some of Its Prominent Men and Pioneers, VII. Syracuse, New York: D. Mason & Co., 1884. Niagara University Library, http://www.niagara.edu/library/buffhist/erie2.html
Society of Architectural Historians, http://www.sah.org/index.php
Texas DAR, Margaret Montgomery Chapter, http://www.texasdar.org/chapters/MargaretMontgomery/
Waldron, Gale. "Joan Williams - A Loudoun Treasure," Loudoun Magazine, v.2 no.8, pg 16, May 2003.
Washington Post, August 18, 1938
Williams Family, Biography File, Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Williams Family Papers (M 010), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Williams, Harrison. The Life, Ancestors and Descendants of Robert Williams of Roxbury in His Majesty's Province of Massachusetts Bay in New England 1607-1693. W.F. Roberts Company: Washington, DC, 1934.
Winslow, Frederick Bradlee, 1873-1937 (letter to Dr. John Collins Warren. Prof. of Surgery. H.M.S., complaining about a "C" in Surgery), Harvard University Library catalog record.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
The Life, Ancestors and Descendents of Robert Williams of Roxbury, 1607-1693, VREF 929.2 WILLIAMS; Legends of Loudoun: An Account of the History and Homes of a Border County of Virginia's Northern Neck, VREF 975.528 WIL; The Redeemed Captive Returning to Zion, VREF 921 WILLIAMS JOHN; The End of the World: A Love Story, VREF Fiction EGG; Winslow Williams Photograph Collection (VC 003), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA; Biography File: Williams Family, Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Separated Material
Loudoun Museum in Leesburg, VA has the following Williams family items: a photograph of Mary Pearce Harrison, photograph of the Loudoun County courthouse by Winslow Williams, a wedding gown, and acetate and glass plate negatives donated by Winslow Williams.
Approximately 26 letters written by Griffin Stedman Williams to his parents during his service in the Civil War are held in the Southern Historical Collection at University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill: Griffin Stedman Williams Papers, #1155-z, Southern Historical Collection, The Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Contents List
- (Box Genealogy; Pearce Family)
  - Genealogy, n.d.
  - Genealogy - pedigree charts, n.d.
  - Genealogy - pedigree charts, n.d.
  - George Pearce, correspondence, 1819-1822
  - Eliza Pearce, correspondence, 1819-1821
  - Eliza Pearce, correspondence, February-July 1822
  - Eliza Pearce, correspondence, August-December 1822
  - Eliza Pearce, correspondence, 1823-1825
  - Eliza Pearce, correspondence, 1827-1834
  - Eliza Pearce, correspondence, 1835-1863
  - Eliza Pearce, correspondence, n.d.
- (Box Pearce Family; Jane Wilson; Harrison Family)
  - Eliza Pearce, bills and receipts, 1821-1829
  - Eliza Pearce, bills and receipts, 1830-1834
  - Eliza Pearce, bills and receipts, 1835-1836
  - Eliza Pearce, bills and receipts, 1837-1838
  - Eliza Pearce, bills and receipts, 1839
  - Eliza Pearce, bills and receipts, 1840-1842
  - Eliza Pearce, bills and receipts, 1843-1849
  - Eliza Pearce, bills and receipts, 1850, 1859
  - Eliza Pearce, bills and receipts, n.d.
  - Eliza Pearce, Navy pension, 1832, 1834, 1837
  - Eliza Pearce, land records, 1850
  - Eliza Pearce, Navy Pension Office claim forms, n.d.
  - Eliza Pearce, calling cards, n.d.
  - Eliza Pearce, stamped envelope, n.d.
  - Jane Wilson, correspondence, 1831, 1848
  - Betsey Cooke Harrison, obituary, 1872
  - Betsey Cooke Harrison, lock of hair, n.d.
  - James C. Harrison, correspondence, 1842-1865
  - James C. Harrison, correspondence, 1869, 1882
  - James C. Harrison, correspondence, n.d.
  - James C. Harrison, invitation, 8 Jan 1850
  - James C. Harrison, membership cards, 1865, n.d.
  - James C. Harrison, railroad pass, 1865
  - James C. Harrison, stamped envelope, 1879, n.d.
  - James C. Harrison, calling card, n.d.
  - James C. Harrison Estate, condolence letter, 1882
  - James C. Harrison Estate, Erie County Savings Bank resolution, 1882
  - James C. Harrison Estate, letters testamentary, 1882
  - James C. Harrison Estate, obituaries, 1882
- (Box Harrison Family)
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, correspondence, 1833-1850
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, correspondence, 1863
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, correspondence, ca.1863-1864
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, correspondence, 1864-1865, 1868
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, correspondence, 1871-1886
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, correspondence, 1887-1890
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, correspondence, n.d.
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, invitation, 15 January 1863
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, receipts, 1867-1869, n.d.
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, prescription, 1870
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, envelopes, n.d.
  - Mary Pearce Harrison, calling cards, n.d.
  - Mary Pearce Harrison Estate, will, 1891
  - Mary Pearce Harrison Estate, correspondence, 1903, 1909
  - Mary Pearce Harrison Estate, assets, 1903, 1909
- (Box Harrison Family, Williams Family)
  - Mary Pearce Harrison Estate, receipts, 1903
  - Mary Pearce Harrison Estate, audits, 1905-1906
  - Mary Pearce Harrison Estate, memoranda, 1909, n.d.
  - Mary Pearce Harrison Estate, release of heirs, 1909
  - Mary Pearce Harrison Estate, receipts, 1909-1911
  - Harrison family, bills and receipts, 1845-1870
  - Harrison family, monograms, n.d.
  - William Williams, correspondence, 1862-1869
  - William Williams, correspondence, 1870-1872
  - William Williams, stock certificates, 1847, 1870, 1872
  - William Williams, agreements, 1848-1869
  - William Williams, Walnut Hill School brochures, ca. 1860
  - William Williams, checks, 1861, 1868-1871
  - William Williams, receipts, 1861-1872, 1874
  - William Williams, life insurance records, 1863, 1867-1876
  - William Williams, Buffalo Fine Art Academy membership certificate, 30 May 1863
  - William Williams, bills, 1865, 1869
  - William Williams, Buffalo Cemetery certificate of ownership, 1866
  - William Williams, St. Joseph Cathedral bell, 1869, 1872
  - William Williams, election certificate, 1870
  - William Williams, Buffalo, New York & Philadelphia Railway election, 1873
  - William Williams, membership cards, 1876, n.d.
  - William Williams, estate papers, 1876
  - William Williams, statement about James McAuliffe, n.d.
  - William Williams, postage stamp, n.d.
  - Louisa Stedman Williams, letter, n.d.
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, correspondence, 1853-1866
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, correspondence, January-March 1867
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, correspondence, April-May 1867
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, correspondence, 1868
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, correspondence, 1869-1881
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, correspondence, 1885-1892
- (Box Williams Family)
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, correspondence, n.d.
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, bet on 1860 election, 1859
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, Civil War special orders, 1863, 1864
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, Civil War orders from F.B. Spinola, 14 December 1863
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, Civil War discharge orders, 10 February 1864
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, card of introduction, 1864
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, receipts, 1864-1886
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, certification of US citizenship, 1869
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, Yokohama Club General Rules, 1869
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, clipping, 1885
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, Civil War pension papers, 1904-1907
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, receipts for care, 1909-1911
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States, 8 Dec 1910
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, obituary, March 1911
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, bookplates, n.d.
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, University School brochure, n.d.
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, envelopes, n.d.
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, business cards, n.d.
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, calling card from James McHenry, n.d.
  - Griffin Stedman Williams, invitation cards, n.d.
  - Griffin Stedman Williams Estate, papers, 1911-1912
  - Griffin Stedman & Mary Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1895, 1890
  - Griffin Stedman & Mary Harrison Williams, wedding invitation, 1871
  - Griffin Stedman & Mary Harrison Williams Estates, correspondence, 1909-1912
  - Mary Harrison Williams, correspondence, January-May 1864
  - Mary Harrison Williams, correspondence, June-July 1864
  - Mary Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1867
  - Mary Harrison Williams, correspondence, February-May 1868
- (Box Williams Family)
  - Mary Harrison Williams, correspondence, June 1868, 1869
  - Mary Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1870-1871
  - Mary Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1878-1890
  - Mary Harrison Williams, correspondence, n.d.
  - Mary Harrison Williams, school certificate, 21 June 1858
  - Mary Harrison Williams, bank books, 1898-1909
  - Mary Harrison Williams, cancelled checks, 1906-1909
  - Mary Harrison Williams, checkbook, 1908-1909
  - Mary Harrison Williams, stamp collection, n.d.
  - Mary Harrison Williams, invitation, n.d.
  - Mary Harrison Williams, cards, n.d.
  - Mary Harrison Williams, calling cards, n.d.
  - Mary Harrison Williams Estate, will, 28 December 1891
  - Mary Harrison Williams Estate, memorandum, 9 July 1906
  - Mary Harrison Williams Estate, inventories, 1909
  - Mary Harrison Williams Estate, surety bond, 4 June 1909
  - Mary Harrison Williams Estate, letter of administration, 11 June 1909
  - Mary Harrison Williams Estate, certificate of administrator, 11 June 1909
  - Mary Harrison Williams Estate, bills and receipts, 1909-1912
  - Mary Harrison Williams Estate, release of heirs, 24 May 1910
  - Gordon Williams, correspondence, 1896-1922
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1882, 1891-1893
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1895
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1896-1898
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1901
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1902
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1903-1904
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1905
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1907
- (Box Williams Family)
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1909
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1910-1912
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1913-1916
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1917-1918
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1919
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1920-1929
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1930, 1932
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1934-1938
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1939
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1940-1941
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1942
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1943
- (Box Williams Family)
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, 1944-1946
  - Harrison Williams, correspondence, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams research, St. Nicholas Parish Church, 1922
  - Harrison Williams research, miscellaneous, 1922, 1937, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams research, Legends of Loudoun, 1934, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams research, Legends of Loudoun, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter I, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter II, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter III, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter IV, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter V, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter VI, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter VII, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter VIII, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter IX, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter X, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter XI, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter XII, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter XIII, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter XIV, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter XV, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams drafts, Legends of Loudoun, Chapter XVI, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams research, The Life, Ancestors and Descendants of Robert Williams of Roxbury, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams research, genealogy, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams research, genealogy, n.d.
- (Box Williams Family)
  - Harrison Williams, invitations, 1893, 1897, n.d.
  - Harrison Williams, bar examination, March 1894
  - Harrison Williams, oath of attorney, 1904
  - Harrison Williams, J.W. Kelly & Co. Distillers pass, 1906-1907
  - Harrison Williams, club memberships, 1906, 1908